Finding Aid for American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County Records 1961-2000
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County Records 1961-2000
American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County.
Washtenaw County, Michigan branch of the American Civil Liberties Union; correspondence, minutes of meetings, and subject files.
85594; Bj 2
3.3 linear feet
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
This record group was donated by the American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County (donor no. 9048 ) in 2000. Portions of the earlier files were donated by individual members of the branch (donor nos. 4353, 4666, 9009 )
The record group is open to research except for membership lists (in box 4) which require permission of the local ACLU board.
Founded in 1920, the American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) is a national organization dedicated to defending individual rights and liberties as set forth in the United States Constitution and its amendments. In this mission, the ACLU has involved itself in a wide variety of legal cases involving issues such as free speech, equal protection under the law, religious liberties, privacy, due process, and voting and reproductive rights. The ACLU is headed by a national board of directors with headquarters in New York City. In the late 1990s, membership was estimated at about 275,000.
National ACLU records note the existence of several local ACLU branches in Michigan as early as 1929. In 1960, the Lansing and Metropolitan Detroit ACLU branches merged and became the ACLU of Michigan. Though technically a state affiliate of the national ACLU, the ACLU of Michigan has considerable independence in management, budget, policy-making, and other internal matters. Organizationally, the ACLU of Michigan is made up of "ACLU" and "ACLU Fund." These two halves exist primarily for budget and tax purposes and State Board members oversee both. The "ACLU Fund" is a non-profit and tax-deductible foundation responsible for public education, the newsletter, and the legal program. The legislative program, management of the state office, and new member recruitment is the responsibility of the "ACLU," which is a Michigan nonprofit organization.
Similar to the mostly independent management of the state level affiliate, each local branch of the ACLU of Michigan conducts its own internal affairs, raises its own funds, stages its own elections, and adopts its own by-laws (though by-laws must be consistent with those of the state affiliate.) Currently, local branches of the ACLU of Michigan include Central Michigan, the Greater Flint Area, the Lansing Area, Metro Detroit, Northwestern Michigan, Oakland County, Southwestern Michigan, Washtenaw County, and Western Michigan.
The Ann Arbor-Washtenaw County Branch of the American Civil Liberties Union was founded in Ann Arbor in 1961. At that time, approximately 300 people from the Ann Arbor area were ACLU members. On October 25, 1961, the branch was organized and a temporary steering committee was chosen. By-laws were adopted on November 20, 1961 and the organization was granted branch status by the ACLU of Michigan State Executive Board on November 26, 1961. Lawrence W. Prakken was elected chairperson of the first executive board. Following Prakken, members of the board of directors have included, among others, local attorneys Jean Ledwith King, Pauline Rothmeyer, and Larry Sperling, University of Michigan natural resources professor Bunyan Bryant, University of Michigan medical school professor Ronald Bishop, former Detroit News cartoonist Art Poinier, University of Michigan journalism professor Wesley Maurer, former Ann Arbor city council Nicholas Kazarinoff, and University of Michigan School of Public Health professor Eugene Feingold.
In 1977, the name of the organization was changed to the American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County. In 1982, local branch membership was estimated at 1,200. Since its inception, the Washtenaw County Branch has been involved in a variety of local issues, including censorship in public schools and libraries; targeted traffic stops by Ann Arbor police, proposed city ordinances on graffiti, panhandling, and curfews; and age and sex discrimination claims. Among these are several cases involving the University of Michigan community, including the University's passing of a student code of conduct and the dismantling of an art exhibit on campus during a conference sponsored by the University's Law School.
The American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County records include minutes, correspondence, newsletters, reports, mailings, and clippings, among other miscellaneous materials. In addition to the Washtenaw branch records, there are also materials from the Michigan state affiliate, the ACLU of Michigan, as well as limited materials from some other local branches and a small amount of material from the national level of the ACLU. The records of this collection are divided into four series: Washtenaw County Branch; ACLU of Michigan; Other Local Branches; and National.
Subjects:
American Civil Liberties Union of Washtenaw County.; Ann Arbor (Mich.); Civil rights--Michigan.; Education--Michigan.; Michigan. Constitutional Convention (1961-1962); Police-community relations--Michigan.; Washtenaw County (Mich.); American Civil Liberties Union of Michigan.
- Washtenaw County Branch
  The Washtenaw County Branch series is divided into two subseries, Administrative and Topical.
  - Administrative
    The Administrative subseries consists of materials related to the organization, governance and management of the Branch, including minutes from executive board meetings, correspondence, by-laws, policy and position statements. Correspondence is split into External and Internal categories. External consists of correspondence to and from individuals and organizations outside of the local branch while Internal consists of correspondence among members of the Washtenaw County Branch, including executive board memos.
    - Budget and Treasurer Reports 1982-1985, 1991 (Box 1)
    - By-Laws 1961-1982, undated (Box 1)
    - Clippings 1962-1987, undated (Box 1)
    - Committees
      - ACLU Committee on Lesbian Women and Gay Men 1981-1983 (Box 1)
      - Equal Rights Committee 1961-1963, undated (Box 1)
      - Other Committees 1962-1963, undated (Box 1)
    - Correspondence
      - External
        - 1959-1962 (Box 1)
        - 1963 (Box 1)
        - 1964 (Box 1)
        - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
        - 1970-1979 (Box 1)
        - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
        - 1990-1993 (Box 1)
        - 1994-1999 (Box 1)
      - Internal
        - 1963-1966 (Box 1)
        - 1971-1975 (Box 1)
        - 1980-1989 (Box 1)
        - 1990-1993 (Box 1)
        - 1994-1999 (Box 1)
    - Elections, Officers, and Boardmembers 1971-1998 (Box 1)
    - Executive Board Roster 1965-1998 (Box 4)
      [Restricted]
    - Fliers and Postings 1984-1985, undated (Box 1)
    - Jerome Strong Award 1996-1998 (Box 1)
    - Mediation Committee Recommendations 1992 (Box 1)
    - Membership Drive 1966 (Box 1)
    - Membership Lists 1961-1971, undated (Box 4)
    - Minutes
      - 1961-1963 (Box 1)
      - 1964-1965 (Box 1)
      - 1966-1969 (Box 1)
      - 1970-1974 (Box 1)
      - 1975 (Box 1)
      - 1976 (Box 1)
      - 1977 (Box 1)
      - 1978 (Box 1)
      - 1979 (Box 1)
      - 1980 (Box 1)
      - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
      - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
      - 1985-1987 (Box 1)
      - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
      - 1990-1992 (Box 2)
      - 1993-1995 (Box 2)
      - 1996-1999 (Box 2)
    - Newsletters 1962-1999 (Box 2)
    - Policy and Position Statements 1962-1987 (Box 2)
    - Press Releases 1964-1965 (Box 2)
    - Reports 1961-1993 (Box 2)
  - Topical
    The Topical subseries consists of files on cases and issues in which the Washtenaw County Branch of the ACLU was either interested or involved. These are organized alphabetically either by subject or individual case name. Of note are materials on the University of Michigan Student Code and the Ann Arbor Public Library's "behavior guidelines." There is also a file of materials on the surveillance practices of the Michigan State Police's "Red Squad," including a copy of the "subversion" file kept by the State Police on the Washtenaw County Branch during the 1960s. Researchers interested in cases listed under the Topical subseries are advised to also consult the Branch's minutes and correspondence under the Administrative subseries for additional information.
    - Ann Arbor Juvenile Curfew Ordinance 1996 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Public Library 1984-1985 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Public Schools, Alcohol Misuse Prevention Study 1991 (Box 2)
    - Ann Arbor Transit Authority Manual 1980 (Box 2)
    - Cowley, Anne 1972-1973 (Box 2)
    - Dexter Community Schools 1962 (Box 2)
    - Hardin, Patrice/Lurie Terrace 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Huron High School, "Independent Emery," 1992 (Box 2)
    - King, Jean Ledwith 1987-1989, undated (Box 2)
    - Lincoln Consolidated School District undated (Box 2)
    - Michigan Child Protection Law 1977 (Box 2)
    - Michigan High School Athletic Association 1973 (Box 2)
    - Michigan Mental Health Code 1980 (Box 2)
    - "Red Squad," 1961-1982 (Box 2)
    - Straight, Inc. 1983-1985 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Law School, "Porn'im'age'ry" exhibit 1993 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan Student Code 1984-1989 (Box 2)
    - Washtenaw County Abortion Rights Coalition 1979-1980 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous 1961-1987 (Box 2)
- ACLU of Michigan
  The ACLU of Michigan series consists of materials from the Michigan state affiliate of the ACLU including minutes from state board meetings, correspondence, by-laws, newsletters, policy and position statements, and materials on budget and membership. Materials from the "ACLU" and the "ACLU Fund" components of the ACLU of Michigan are interfiled.
  - Budget and Membership
    - 1964-1971 (Box 2)
    - 1978 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1996 (Box 2)
  - By-Laws 1960s, 1987, undated (Box 2)
  - Clippings 1980-1989, undated (Box 2)
  - Correspondence
    - 1963-1979 (Box 2)
    - 1980-1983 (Box 2)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1994 (Box 3)
    - 1995-1996 undated (Box 3)
  - Directories 1987-1997 (Box 4)
  - Election, State Board 1986, undated (Box 3)
  - Fliers and Postings 1967-1992 (Box 3)
  - Legal Dockets 1978, 1990 (Box 3)
  - Minutes
    - 1961-1969 (Box 3)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 3)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 3)
    - 1980-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - 1995-1999 (Box 3)
  - New Board Member Orientation 1993 (Box 3)
  - Newsletters
    - 1962-1970 (Box 3)
    - 1978-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1991-2000 (Box 3)
  - Planning 1967-1994 (Box 3)
  - Policy and Position Statements 1966-1991 (Box 3)
  - Policy Guide Revisions 1993-1996 (Box 3)
  - Press Releases 1993-1994 (Box 3)
  - Reports 1978-1996 (Box 3)
  - Rosters 1978, undated (Box 3)
  - Self-Assessment 1984, 1986, 1990-1991 (Box 3)
  - Women's Rights Committee 1990-1994 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous 1978-1994 (Box 3)
- Other Local Branches
  The Other Local Branches series is divided into two subseries, the Oakland County Branch and Miscellaneous Branches and Chapters. Miscellaneous Branches and Chapters consists of limited materials from the Lansing Area, the Northwestern Michigan, the Greater Flint, the Metro Detroit, the Saginaw Valley, and the Kalamazoo Area branches and chapters.
  - Oakland County Branch 1982-1994 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous. Branches and Chapters 1971-1993 (Box 3)
- National
  The National subseries consists solely of materials from the National Biennial Conference of the ACLU held in Ann Arbor in 1963.
  - Biennial Conference of the ACLU, Ann Arbor 1968 (Box 3)